<?xml version='1.0'?> 
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY date "October 2008"> 
  <!ENTITY appversion "0.6.0"> 
  <!ENTITY app "<application>xfce4-power-manager</application>">
]>

<article id="xfce4-power-manager" lang="en">
<!-- Header --> 
<articleinfo>

  <title>Xfce 4 Power Manager</title>
 
  <copyright>
    <year>2008</year> <holder>Ali Abdallah</holder>
  </copyright>


<authorgroup>

    <author>
      <firstname>Ali</firstname> <surname>Abdallah</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<address><email>ali.slackware@gmail.com</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    
<!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
maintainers, etc. Commented out by default.

    <othercredit role="translator">
      <firstname>Latin</firstname> <surname>Translator 1</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname>
	<address><email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address>
      </affiliation> <contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
    </othercredit>
-->

</authorgroup>

<releaseinfo>This manual describes &app; version &appversion;
</releaseinfo>

</articleinfo>

  <!-- extra space -->
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
    
<sect1 id="xfpm-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  The Xfce4 power manager is a part of the Xfce goodies project and features cpu frequency control,
  battery monitoring, monitor DPMS control, LCD brightness control, lid sleep and power buttons controls.
  All those features can be controlled from the user interface settings dialog.
  <sect2 id="xfpm-started">
  <title>Getting Started</title>
  <para>To launch the Power Manager you need to run the following command &app; -r you can do from the xfce run
  command by pressing ALT-F2, or you go to the Xfce settings manager and you click on the Power Manager item
  , a popup should be displayed only if the power manager isn't already running to ask you if you want to. 
  Once the power manager is launched for the first time, it'll place a autostart desktop file in you .config/autostart
  so like that it gets launched automatically second time you log into your Xfce desktop.
  </para> 
  </sect2> 
</sect1>

 <!-- extra space -->
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
 
<sect1 id="xfpm-configuration">
  <title>Power Manager Configuration</title>
  <para>
  Almost all the &app; items are configurable from the configuration window, laptop users can set up 
  a power profile for two different modes “on battery power” and “on ac power”, desktop users still can change 
  DPMS settings and CPU frequency.
  </para>
  <para>
  The settings dialog differs from one system to another depends on the computer (PC,laptop,...) and on
  the available manageabale interfaces.  
  </para>
  <para>
  In this section we will describe the possible configuration for the power manager.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="xfpm-general">
  <title>General Settings</title>
  <para><figure float="0">
	<title>General settings</title>
	<screenshot><mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/general-settings.png" format="png"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
	<phrase></phrase>
	</textobject>
	</mediaobject></screenshot>
	</figure></para>
	<para>
	Here you can select the configuration of the system tray icon, enable/disable cpu frequency and DPMS controls, 
	typical reason to disable DPMS control for example if you are watching a movie.	
	</para>
  </sect2>
	  
  
  <sect2 id="xfpm-cpu">
   <title>CPU Settings</title>
   <para><figure float="0">
	<title>CPU Linux governors</title>
	<screenshot><mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/cpu-settings.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
	<phrase></phrase>
	</textobject>
	</mediaobject></screenshot>
	</figure></para>
	<para>
	The linux governors found in the system are listed for choice as a radio buttons,
	if the acpi_cpufreq module is not loaded in the kernel or the cpu itself doesn't support
	changes in it's frequency these options might not be shown.
	</para>
	<para>Here's a brief descritption on linux cpu governors</para>
		
<variablelist>

   <varlistentry>
	<term>Performance:</term>
	<listitem>
	<para> Set the CPU to it's maximum frequency. will consume more power, 
	and it's not ideal when running on battery.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Powersave:</term>
	<listitem>
	<para> 
	Set the CPU to it's minimum frequency, ideal when running on battery power.	
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Userspace:</term>
	<listitem>
	<para> In this governor, allows the user, or any userspace
	program running with UID "root", to set the CPU to a specific frequency.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>		
	
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Ondemand:</term>
	<listitem>
	<para> What you want is what you get. sets the CPU depending on the
	current usage.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>	
	
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Conservative:</term>
	<listitem>
	<para> 
	 Same as Ondemand but differs in behaviour in that it gracefully increases and decreases 
	 the CPU speed rather than jumping to max speed the moment there is any load on the CPU.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>	
	
</variablelist>
<para>
NOTE:In &app; version &appversion; only Linux is supported for changing the CPU frequency.
</para>

</sect2>  
  
  <sect2 id="xfpm-battery">
    <title>Battery settings</title>
	<para><figure float="0">
	<title>Battery settings</title>
	<screenshot><mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/battery-settings.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
	<phrase></phrase>
	</textobject>
	</mediaobject></screenshot>
</figure></para>
	<para>
	The user can select the percentage of the battery to be considered as critical, usually this is for a laptop or
	UPS battery, this option is important as for a broken battery for example, the battery when it is 10% charged 
	can last	5 minutes, so the user can increase the level at wish the battery charge will be considered critical.    
   </para>
   <para>
   The user can define an action to be taken by the power manager in case the battery wish is giving the main power
   for the computer reaches a critical charge level.
   </para> 
   The battery notification is a way to notify the user when the battery state changes ( ex: battery charge is full )
   <para>
   
   </para>
  </sect2>  
  
  <sect2 id="xfpm-button">
    <title>Keyboard shortcuts</title>
	<para><figure float="0">
	<title>button control</title>
	<screenshot><mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/button-settings.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
	<phrase></phrase>
	</textobject>
	</mediaobject></screenshot>
</figure></para>
   For those buttons you can define an action to be taken by the power manager when happen to press one of them, 
   for example when you close the laptop screen. 
    
  </sect2>  
  
  <sect2 id="xfpm-monitor">
   <title>Monitor settings</title>
   <para><figure float="0">
	<title>Monitor DPMS and lcd brightness</title>
	<screenshot><mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/monitor-settings.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
	<phrase></phrase>
	</textobject>
	</mediaobject></screenshot>
</figure></para>
	<para>
	DPMS is an old X extension that allows standby/suspend/turn off options of the monitor, usually the timeouts 
	have to be succesitive, so standby timeout less than suspend timeout and so on, but one always can disable any option.
	</para>
	<para>
	For a laptop users by clicking on the checkbox allows the power manager to reduce the screen luminosity when
	it detects that system in running on battery power and set it again to the maximum value when system is running
	on AC power.
	</para>
	</sect2>  
</sect1>

<!-- extra space -->
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
  
<sect1 id="xfpm-systray">
<title>System Tray Icon</title>
</sect1>


<!-- extra space -->
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
     
<sect1 id="xfpm-notify">
<title>Notification</title>
</sect1>

 <!-- extra space -->
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
  
<sect1 id="xfpm-faq">
  <title>FAQ</title>
  <variablelist>

   <varlistentry>
	<term>Q: Why the icons look very similar to the icon of gnome power manager</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>A: No, they are not similar, they are the same, just there is no point of re-drawing icons,
	gnome power manager icons are good enough. not all of them are used.  
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	 <varlistentry>
	<term>Q: What is the difference between suspend and hibernate</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>A: Suspend if a power save feature, when suspending, the computer is still using power,
	since the running applications are kept in the memory, but is the lowest power level the computer
	can use. 
	Hibernate saves the system state on the hard drive and turns off the power, when you start up your computer
	again those data will be loaded and the system comes up. 
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	 <varlistentry>
	<term>Q: Why the options of suspend/hibernate are not there or i can't select them</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>A: Many possible reasons, for example your kernel doesn't or it's not compiled with suspend/hibernate options.
	Another possible reason is the fact that you are not allowed to use them.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	 <varlistentry>
	<term>Q: How the power manager actually suspend or hibernate my system</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>A: The power manager checks if the user is allowed to, then send a DBus message to HAL asking to suspend
	/hibernate, usually the methods used to suspend or hibernate used by HAL is a script located in /usr/lib/hal/scripts/YourOs.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	 <varlistentry>
	<term>Q: If the power manager puts the computer in hibernate because my battery charge is critical what will happen
	if i turn it on again without plugging my adapter</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>A: Nothing actually, the power manager had take the action defined by the user already and understands
	that the user insist of using the laptop so in the best cases it'll display a popup with options that user can do.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	 <varlistentry>
	<term>Q: I select the option of the lcd brightness control but i don't see the brightness changing when i switch 
	from AC adapter to battery power</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>A: You kernel doesn't have the right driver, or the driver isn't loaded.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		
</variablelist>
</sect1>  

 <!-- extra space -->
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
<sect1 id="xfpm-about">
  <title>About &app;</title>
  <para>
	This power manager was written following the philosophy of Xfce, having leight weight application that does
	what the user expect for it.
	</para>

  <para>To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this application or
    this manual, use the bug tracking system at <ulink 
      url="http://bugzilla.xfce.org/" 
      type="http">http://bugzilla.xfce.org/</ulink>. 
  </para>

  <para>If you have questions about the use or installation of this package,
    please ask on the <ulink 
      url="http://lunar-linux.org/mailman/listinfo/xfce"
      type="http">xfce</ulink> mailing list. Development discussion takes
    place on the <ulink 
      url="http://lunar-linux.org/mailman/listinfo/xfce4-dev"
      type="http">xfce4-dev</ulink> mailing list
    or on  <ulink 
      url="http://lunar-linux.org/mailman/listinfo/xfce4-goodies-dev"
      type="http">xfce4-goodies-dev</ulink> mailing list.
  </para>
  
</sect1>  

 <!-- extra space -->
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
  <para> This program is distributed under the terms of the
    GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation; 
    either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  </para>

  <para>You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License 
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software 
    Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, 
    USA.
  </para>

</article>